Inventory of the William Martin notes
Hoover Institution Archives
William Martin notes
1915-1933
XX420
Hoover Institution Archives
5 manuscript boxes (2 linear feet)
Summaries of interviews of European diplomats and statesmen, relating to European and world military, political, and diplomatic events during and after World War I. In part, photocopy.
Martin, William, 1888-1934.
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical/Historical Note
WIlliam Louis Martin was born in Geneva, in 1888, of Swiss parents. He was educated at Geneva and Berlin and, in 1908, earned a degree in law, the following year in political science, and, in 1910, his doctorate in law. From 1907 to 1914 he was in Berlin as a correspondent for the Journal de Genève and for the Journal des Débats (Paris). During the first year of World War I he was attached to the General Staff of the Swiss army. He was the Paris correspondent for the Journal de Genève in 1915 and 1916 and political lead writer from 1917 to 1919. In 1918, as a member of a Swiss press mission, he traveled widely through the United States. In 1919 he was in the Section of Information of the Secretaries of the League of Nations and for the next four years he was technical adviser for the International Labor Office. In 1924 he became the Foreign Editor of the Journal de Genève.
Martin was a professor ad interim of the diplomatic history of Switzerland and International Law at the University of Geneva. He wrote the La Crise Politique de l'Allemagne Contemporaine (1913); Sur les routes de la Victoire (1916); and Histoire de la Suisse (1926). He contributed to many English and American newspapers and magazines, including The Atlantic Monthly, The Forum, the New York World, The Christian Science Monitor, The Spectator, The Contemporary Review, and The Quarterly Review.
Scope and Content of Collection
Summaries of interviews of European diplomats and statesmen, relating to European and world military, political, and diplomatic events during and after World War I. In part, photocopy.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Europe--Politics and government--1918-1945.; Journalists.; World politics--1919-1932.; World War, 1914-1918--Diplomatic history.
- Inventory (Box-folder 1: 1)
- Martin, William. Notes de Guerre. Hoover War Library (Box 1-2)
  - 1915-1917 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Supplement to the first two volumes (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - November 1919 and December 1920 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - 1918-1920 (Box-folder 2: 1)
- Bound Supplements, Janurary - December 1918 (Box-folder 2: 2)
- Unbound Supplements, January- October 1919 (Box-folder 2: 3)
- William Martin's Conversations, 1924-1933
  - Register of William Martin's Conversations (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - June-December, pages 1-160, 1924 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - January-December, pages 161-418, 1925 (Box-folder 3: 2)
  - January-December, pages 419-633, 1926 (Box-folder 3: 3)
  - January-December, pages 634-907, 1927 (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - January-December, pages 908-1011, 1928 (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - April-December, pages 1012-1170, 1929 (Box-folder 4: 2)
  - January-December, pages 1171-1400, 1930 (Box-folder 4: 3)
  - January-December, pages 1401-1615, 1931 (Box-folder 4: 4)
  - January-December, pages 1616-1851, 1932 (Box-folder 5: 1)
  - January-December, pages 1852-1968, 1933 (Box-folder 5: 2)